Finding Aid for Dept. of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education (University of Michigan) records, 1919-1993.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education (University of Michigan) records 1919-1993, 1963-1985
University of Michigan. Dept. of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education.
15 linear feet
9444 Bimu 2 n
Dept. of Postgraduate Medicine established at the University of Michigan in 1927 as part of a state wide effort to provide continuing medical education to practicing physicians. In 1946 the Affiliated Hospital program began, providing decentralized medical training for interns, residents, and community practitioners. Documents the development and administration of the affiliated hospital program, and material on key affiliations including Henry Ford Hospital, St. Joseph Mercy Hospital, Veterans Administration Hospital, and Wayne County General Hospital, as well as hospitals throughout the state. Records documenting the early use of medical television are present as are records of the Medical Center House Officers Committee, and speeches by James D. Bruce.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received from two sources: Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education (Donor # 8226 in 1994 and the Towsley family (# 4289 in 1993 and 1994.
The Dept. of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Dept. of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 11
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 11
The records of the University of Michigan Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education were received from two separate sources. Dr. Roland G. Hiss provided records pertaining to the affiliated hospital program which he was in charge of since 1976. Hiss began his affiliation with the department in 1967 and has served as chairman since 1981. Additional departmental records were separated from the personal papers of Harry A. Towsley. Towsley was appointed to the department in 1948 to oversee the decentralized graduate medical education program and served as chairman from 1967 until his retirement in 1971.
When the University of Michigan Medical School offered its first courses in the fall of 1850, the field of medical science was poised for a tremendous explosion of knowledge. Rapid advances in medicine and medical practices soon made the need for postgraduate medical education readily apparent. The University of Michigan Board of Regents acknowledged this need as early as 1878 when they authorized the faculty of the Medical School to admit medical graduates into undergraduate courses (Regent's Proceedings, January 22, 1878).
The admission of graduates into undergraduate courses was rescinded in 1892 when the Medical School began to offer graduate courses. A system of summer courses was instituted in 1902, which offered refresher courses and the introduction of new medical practices and procedures both for credit and non-credit. Despite these efforts there was growing demand for greater continuity and more academic direction of the program.
In January 1926, representatives of the University of Michigan Medical School, Detroit College of Medicine and Surgery (Wayne State University School of Medicine), and the Michigan State Medical Society met in Ann Arbor to consider ways of meeting the rapidly growing need for postgraduate study in Michigan. A committee was formed to study the problem and a recommendation was made for a program of postgraduate education to be assumed by the University of Michigan because of its state support.
The recommendation was placed before the Board of Regents, who voted on June 24, 1927, to establish a Department of Postgraduate Medicine within the Medical School. Dr. James D. Bruce was named the head of the new department. Although he did not receive any additional salary he was given an expense budget of $2,000 and office space in the administrative wing of the University Hospital.
The first postgraduate courses were offered from May 27 to June 24, 1929, at the Receiving Hospital, Herman Keifer Hospital, and Children's Hospital in Detroit. Twenty-four doctors registered for the course in internal medicine and twenty for the surgery course. In 1938/39, during the program's tenth year, fifteen short, intensive courses were presented throughout the state including several summer sessions. Total enrollment in these courses was 2,392, including practitioners from all over Michigan and several other states.
Increasing medical specialization helped to make the residency a vital component of postgraduate medicine. In 1927 when the department was founded there were only 270 hospitals nationwide offering a total of 1,699 residency openings. By 1945 the number had grown to 734 hospitals offering 8,930 residencies, and in 1976 there were 1,702 hospitals providing 65,046 residencies. (Graduate Medical Education: Proposals for the Eighties, Association of American Medical Colleges, 1980).
An influx of returning World War II servicemen resuming their medical education and specialty training triggered the development of the Decentralized Residency Training Program in October 1946. This program, also known as the Affiliated Hospital Program, was funded by a grant from the W.K. Kellogg Foundation and was designed to upgrade the quality of intern and resident (house officer) training in Michigan and to improve the distribution of physicians throughout the state. The program provided a link between the Medical School and other health education providers as hospitals in Detroit, Saginaw, Grand Rapids, Pontiac, Battle Creek, Kalamazoo, Lansing, Benton Harbor, Traverse City and Midland became affiliated with the University of Michigan.
On March 27, 1969, the Towsley Center for Continuing Medical Education was formally dedicated. The new facility, which replaced the inadequate space in the University Hospital, included the 518-seat Dow Auditorium and the 114-seat Sheldon Lecture Room. The addition of this facility greatly strengthened the delivery of intramural education and added a major audio-visual component to continuing medical education.
During the 1970/71 academic year the department underwent a major program review. The Ad Hoc Committee to Review the Department of Postgraduate Medicine, chaired by Dr. Chris Zarafonetis, issued several recommendations that resulted in significant expansion and restructuring of the department. The name of the department was officially changed to the Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education to reflect these new changes. The review committee also recommended that the teaching activities be expanded at affiliated community hospitals as well as in undergraduate medical student teaching and continuing education of allied health professionals. The recommendations further stressed the addition of research in the areas of teaching, learning, and evaluation of health services.
In 1977, as the department celebrated its fiftieth anniversary, the organizational structure consisted of five offices: Office of Educational Resources and Research, Office of Extramural Education, Office of Intramural Education, Office of Allied Health Education, and Office of Health Care Delivery Research. That year the department's programs reached nearly 7,000 physicians and medical students.
Grant-funded research components such as the Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center were added to the departmental responsibilities, administered by the Office of Extramural Education. From 1984 to 1991 the department published the Michigan Postgraduate Review, promoting further outreach (The Medical Center Journal, 1964-1980, also carried postgraduate medicine news and articles).
The present structure is composed of three major offices or divisions (Office of Educational Resources and Research, Office of Extramural Education, and Office of Continuing Medical Education), with a three-fold mission of educational support, outreach, and continuing education underscored by research.
Chairmen of the Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education
1927-1942 James D. Bruce
1942-1954 Howard H. Cummings
1954-1967 John M. Sheldon
1967-1971 Harry A. Towsley
1971-1974 Neal Vanselow
1974-1980 William Harlan
1981-1982 Roland G. Hiss (Acting)
1982- Roland G. Hiss
_________________
Sources Consulted
Bruce, James D, "Postgraduate Education in Medicine," Journal of the Michigan State Medical Society, June 1937*
________, "Continuing Professional Education," Journal of the American Medical
Association 110, April 23, 1938*
________, "Postgraduate Medical Education," Journal of the Association of American Medical Colleges, May 1941*
Karr, Joan Mason, "The Department of Postgraduate Medicine: A History and Interpretation of its Development" (Ph.D. Dissertation, U of M), 1979
Kelly, Mabel F., "University of Michigan Department of Postgraduate Medicine," (unpublished history) ca. 1967*
Sheldon, John M, Thomas C. Flotte, and Mabel F. Kelly, "Postgraduate Medical Education at the University of Michigan Medical Center," Postgraduate Medicine 27, January 1960*
Towsley, Harry A., "University of Michigan Plan for Postgraduate Medical Education," Journal of the American Medical Association, 164 May 25, 1957*
________, "Remarks at Dedication of the Towsley Center for Continuing Medical ," Education," March 27, 1969*
Wilkinson, Charles F., Jr., "Hospitals' New Role as Michigan Decentralizes," Hospitals, February 1947*
________, "The General Practitioner," Journal of the American Medical Society 137, July 10, 1948*
________, "Michigan's Decentralized Resident Training Programs," Journal of the Michigan State Medical Society 47, September 1948*
Annual Report of the Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education, 1976-77 (Fiftieth Anniversary Issue)
"Postgrad Medicine," University Record, Vol. XIV, No. 1, October 1958*
* Copies of cited sources are located in Box 1 of this record group.
The records of the University of Michigan Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education, dating from 1919 to 1993, offer a partial picture of the development of the department and the subsequent effort to provide continuing medical education to practicing physicians and residents. These records generally contain little information about intramural programming, primarily focusing on the affiliated hospital program and the training of interns and residents (house officers). The records are also indicative of the varied responsibilities held by the department over time (i.e., administration of Medical Center Alumni Society).
The records were received in two separate accessions. The first accession, received from the Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education in 1994 is located in boxes 1-10. Material received in 1996 are located in boxes 12-15. Restricted files from both accessions have been removed to box 11.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education.; Henry Ford Hospital.; Veterans Administration Hospital (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Wayne County General Hospital.; St. Joseph Mercy Hospital (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Medicine--Study and teaching (Graduate); Residents (Medicine)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Interns (Medicine)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Towsley, Harry A.; Bruce, James D. (James Deacon), 1872-1946.
Genre Terms:
College publications.
- Historical/Reference Files
  Historical/Reference File contains both primary and secondary documentation pertaining to the history and development of the Department of Postgraduate Medicine. The reference file was assembled and "catalogued" by Joan Mason Karr in 1977 while researching her dissertation ("The Department of Postgraduate Medicine: A History and Interpretation of its Development," 1979) and has been retained in the order in which it was compiled. A list of catalogued files accompanies the material. Original documentation includes correspondence from the Kellogg Foundation (1946-1951) relating to the development of the decentralized graduate medical education program, and records of the dedication of the Towsley Center for Continuing Medical Education. Also of note is a thirty-six page unpublished history of the department written by Mabel Kelly, c. 1967. Kelly was the department's secretary from 1929 to 1967.
  - History of Postgraduate Medicine February 6, 1984 (Box 1)
    (Presentation by Harry A. Towsley to "Dunworkin' Meeting")
  - Miscellaneous History and Notes 1892-1977 (Box 1)
  - Reprints (various histories) 1936-1960 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Department of Postgraduate Medicine by Mabel Kelly circa 1967 (Box 1)
  - Reference File
    - List of Catalogued Reference Files 1977 (Box 1)
    - "University of Michigan Plan for Postgraduate Medical Education," Journal of the American Medical Association, May 1957 (Box 1)
    - "Postgraduate Medical Education at the University of Michigan," Postgraduate Medicine, January 1960 (Box 1)
    - Dedication-Towsley Center for Continuing Medical Education March 27, 1969
      - Invitations 1969 (Box 1)
      - Harry A. Towsley Remarks 1969 (Box 1)
      - Guest Book 1969 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Annual Report of Department of Postgraduate Medicine 1959/60 (Box 1)
    - John M. Sheldon Bibliography 1948-1966 (Box 1)
    - Postgraduate Medicine Programs 1934-1952 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, Dr. James D. Bruce to Dr. C.F. Murbach 1931-1932 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Postgraduate Medical Education 1932-1944 (Box 1)
    - Publicity 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - W.K. Kellogg Foundation 1946-1951 (Box 1)
    - Decentralized Graduate Medical Education 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - Questionnaire sent out after 1946/47 Course (Box 1)
    - Charles F. Wilkinson, Jr. 1947-1948 (Box 1)
- Administrative Files
  The series Administrative Files provides a partial overview of issues in graduate medical education from the mid-1950s to the late 1980s. These alphabetically arranged files include accreditation material, annual reports (1966/67-1968/69), correspondence (1964-1971), records of Dean's Staff meetings, and information on postgraduate medical instruction throughout Michigan.
  - American Medical Association Council on Medical Education Accreditation 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Annual Reports 1966/67-1968/69 (see Historical/Reference Files for 1959/60 and printed works for 1976/77 and later) (Box 2)
  - Association of American Medical Colleges Accreditation Visit 1967 (Box 2)
  - Audit Report, Tuition Income 1965 (Box 2)
  - Birch, Larry 1966-1970 (Box 2)
  - Budget 1967-1970 (Box 2)
  - Clerkships 1975, 1977-1978, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Color Camera 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Postgraduate Medical Education (see Michigan State Medical Society) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1964-1971, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Cottage Hospital (Grosse Point Farms, MI) 1962-1967 (Box 2)
  - Dean's Staff Meetings 1976-1984, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Diabetes Research and Training Center (DRTC)
    - Continuation Grant Planning 1980 (Box 2)
    - Site Visit 1981 (Box 2)
    - Recruitment Process 1985 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of Postgraduate Courses 1965 (Box 2)
  - Green Committee (Critical Needs of the State of Michigan for Higher Education) 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - Health Manpower in Michigan 1974-1978, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Internship Review Study 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - Medical Center Journal, 1968-1971 (Box 3)
  - Medical Staff Reorganization 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Association for Graduate and Postgraduate Medical Education 1965-1968 (Box 3)
  - The Michigan Physician and His Continuing Education 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Michigan State Medical Society (MSMS)
    - Committee on Postgraduate Medical Education 1964-1965 (see Historical/Reference Files for 1932-1944) (Box 3)
  - Oakland Health Education Program 1973-1984 (Box 3)
  - Objectives of Internal Medicine Residency 1969 (Box 3)
  - Pediatrics 1968-1970 (Box 3)
  - Postgraduate Medicine Retreat 1968, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Secretariat for Regional Medical Programs at the University of Michigan 1970-1971
    - Michigan Association for Regional Medical Programs (MARMP) Grant Submission 1969 (Box 3)
  - Statistical Reports 1969/70-1970/71 (Box 3)
  - Teaching Compensation 1967-1970 (Box 3)
- Affiliated Hospitals
  The Affiliated Hospitals series, which comprises the bulk of the record group, contains information on the origins of the affiliated hospital program and the major affiliations with the University of Michigan Medical School. Annual reports from 1948/49 through 1951/52 richly document the genesis of decentralized graduate medical education and resident instruction. These files, arranged alphabetically by hospital name, include Henry Ford Hospital, St. Joseph Mercy Hospital (now part of the Catherine McAuley Health Services), Veterans Administration Hospital, and Wayne County General Hospital (later Westland Hospital). These records describe the curriculum and training of interns and residents and often underscore the sensitive relationships between the Medical School and the affiliated hospitals. The files are particularly rich in committee minutes including joint liaison committees and various task forces.
  - Administrative Files
    - Affiliation Changes 1968-1971 (Box 3)
    - Affiliation Checklist 1979 (Box 3)
    - Affiliated Hospitals Survey and Statistics, [1947-1971], 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Affiliated Hospitals Miscellaneous 1967-1971 (Box 3)
    - Affiliated Hospital Payments 1969 (Box 3)
    - Affiliated Hospitals Payment Schedules 1984-1987 (Box 3)
  - Annual Reports
    - Mimeographed Material 1946-1948 (Box 3)
    - Annual Report of the Program of Decentralized Graduate Medical Education 1948/49 (Box 3)
    - Annual Report of the Program of Decentralized Graduate Medical Education 1949/50 (Box 3)
    - Affiliated Hospital Resident Training Program 1950/51 (Box 3)
    - General Practice Intern Training Program 1950/51 (Box 3)
    - Affiliated Hospital Resident Training Program 1951/52 (Box 3)
  - Affiliated Hospitals (Arranged by Hospital)
    - Affiliated Hospitals 1987-1991 (Box 4)
      (Includes Beyer, Chelsea, Grand Rapids Area Medical Education Center (GRAMEC), Oakland Health Education Program (OHEP), Southwestern Michigan Area Health Education Center (SMAHEC), Kalamazoo Center for Medical Studies (KCMS))
    - Chelsea Community Hospital Liaison Committee 1983-1984, 1989-1991 (Box 4)
    - Henry Ford Hospital
      - Affiliation Negotiations 1968-1972 (Box 4)
      - Boston Consulting Group Report 1972 (Box 4)
      - Director of Medical Education Search 1983-1984 (Box 11)
      - Finances 1976-1981 (Box 4)
      - Ford Foundation 1980 (Box 4)
      - Graduate Medical Education Task Force 1976-1981 (Box 4)
      - Joint Committee on Affiliation/Liaison Committee 1976-1988 (Box 4)
      - Neurology Department 1980 (Box 4)
      - Small Group Meetings 1980-1981 (Box 4)
      - General 1975-1993, 13 folders (Box 4)
    - St. Joseph Mercy Hospital
      - Affiliation Task Force 1972 (Box 4)
      - Ambulance Service 1981-1983 (Box 4)
      - Burn Unit Task Force 1976-1979 (Box 4)
      - Finances 1976-1984 (Box 4)
      - Gynecology-Oncology 1981-1983 (Box 4)
      - House Officers Contract 1976-1980, 1984 (Box 4)
      - Institutional Liaison Committee 1976-1984 (Box 4)
      - Lithotripter 1984-1987 (Box 4)
      - Neonatology Committee 1978-1980 (Box 4)
      - Obstetrics and Gynecology 1979-1989 (Box 5)
      - Ophthalmology Shared Services Advisory Board 1979-1980 (Box 5)
      - Ophthalmology Program Liaison Committee 1980-1981 (Box 5)
      - Pediatrics 1973-1977, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Professional Interrelationships Task Force 1980-1982 (Box 5)
      - Radiation Therapy 1985 (Box 5)
      - Rehabilitation Center 1980-1986 (Box 5)
      - General 1970-1993, 14 folders (Box 5)
    - Veterans Administration Hospital
      - Affiliated Hospital 1977 (Box 5)
      - Anesthesia Contract 1976-1985 (Box 5)
      - Bonus Management 1975, 1988 (Box 5)
      - Chief of Medicine 1976 (Box 5)
      - Chief of Staff Search 1981, 1984-1985 (Box 11)
      - Chief of Staff Search, 1988 (Box 5)
        [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2018 ]
      - Conflict of Interest 1985-1986 (Box 5)
      - VA Dean's Committee 1977-1987 (Box 5)
      - Education, Assistant Chief of Staff for 1981-1982 (Box 11)
      - Finances, 1975-77 1981-1983 (Box 5)
      - FTE Study 1988 (Box 5)
      - GAO Review 1977 (Box 5)
      - House Officer Allocation 1977-1985 (Box 5)
      - House Officer Contract 1975-1989 (Box 5)
      - Mancini (John) Space Issue 1987-1988 (Box 6)
      - MEDIP (Medical District Initiated Planning Process) 1981-1983 (Box 6)
      - Neurology 1978-1979 (Box 6)
      - Pharmacy Cost Study 1988-1989 (Box 11)
        [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2019 ]
      - Psychiatry 1978-1982 (Box 6)
      - Radiation Therapy 1976, 1983-1988 (Box 6)
      - Radiology, 1979-1985 (Box 11)
      - Radiology 1988-1989 (Box 11)
      - Report on VA Relationship 1986 (Box 6)
      - Rehabilitation Medicine Service 1988 (Box 6)
      - Retreat 1988 (Box 6)
      - Saginaw VA Affiliation Proposal 1984 (Box 6)
      - Shared Equipment Proposal 1988 (Box 6)
      - Tour of Duty in VA 1983 (Box 6)
      - General 1974-1991, 14 folders (Box 6)
    - Wayne County General Hospital/Westland Medical Center (Box 7)
      - Acquisition Analysis October 24, 1983 (Box 7)
      - Acquisition Plan and Framework for Business Operating Plan November 1983 (Box 7)
      - Affiliation Agreement 1977-1978 (Box 7)
      - Anesthesia 1976-1982 (Box 7)
      - Background, [1960-74] 1974-1976 (Box 7)
      - Contingency Planning 1978-1980
        - Wayne County Payroll Default 1979 (Box 7)
      - Coordinating Committee 1979-1981 (Box 7)
      - County Organized Professionals 1979-1980 (Box 7)
      - Faculty Parity Study 1976 (Box 7)
      - (New) Governance Study 1980-1981 (Box 7)
      - Greater Detroit Area Hospital Council (GDAHC) 1976-1978 (Box 7)
      - GDAHC Governance Report 1980 (Box 7)
      - House Officer Contract 1979-1984 (Box 7)
      - Liaison Committee 1977-1982, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Malpractice 1975-1977 (Box 7)
      - Medical Service Plan 1976-1981, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Wayne County General Hospital/Westland Medical Center (cont.)
      - Neurology 1977 (Box 7)
      - New University Hospital Planing 1979 (Box 7)
      - Orthopedics 1976-1977 (Box 7)
      - Radiology 1976-1982 (Box 7)
      - Reallocation of Students and House Officers 1984 (Box 7)
      - Surgery 1976-1980 (Box 8)
      - University Medical Affiliated, P.C. (UMAPC) 1982-1985, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - General 1976-1981, 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Westland Medical Center
      - Affiliation Draft 1984-1985 (Box 8)
      - Contract Renewal 1985-1987 (Box 8)
      - General 1984-1985 (Box 8)
- Medical Center Alumni Society
  Indicative of the department's varied role are files of the Medical Center Alumni Society. The department had administrative oversight of this society for roughly a decade beginning in the mid-1960s. These files contain modest information on reunion planning, fund raising, and the general operation of the society.
  - Alumni Conference 1963 (Box 8)
  - Board of Governors, 1963-64 1969-1971, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Reunions 1964 (Box 8)
  - Reunions 1965, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Alumni Awards Committee 1967-1972 (Box 8)